<!-- $Id$ -->
<chapter id="install"><title>Obtaining, Compiling, Installing, and Removing Nmap</title>
<indexterm class="startofrange" id="install-indexterm"><primary>installation</primary></indexterm>

<sect1 id="inst-intro"><title>Introduction</title>

<para>Nmap can often be installed or upgraded with a single command,
so don't let the length of this chapter scare you.  Most readers will
use the table of contents to skip
directly to sections that concern them.  This chapter describes how to install
Nmap on many platforms, including both source
code compilation and binary installation methods.  Graphical and
command-line versions of Nmap are described and contrasted.
Nmap removal instructions are also provided in case you change your
mind.</para>

<sect2 id="inst-already"><title>Testing Whether Nmap is Already Installed</title>
<indexterm><primary>Nmap</primary><secondary>checking if installed</secondary></indexterm>
<para>The first step toward obtaining Nmap is to check whether you already
have it.  Many free operating system distributions (including most
Linux and BSD systems) come with Nmap packages, although they may not be
installed by default.  On Unix systems, open a terminal window and try executing the command
<command>nmap <option>--version</option></command>.
If Nmap exists and is in your
<envar>PATH</envar>,<indexterm><primary><envar>PATH</envar> environment variable</primary></indexterm>
you should see output similar to that in <xref linkend="ex-checking-for-nmap" xrefstyle="select: label nopage" />.</para>

<indexterm><primary>version number of Nmap</primary><see><option>--version</option></see></indexterm>

<example id="ex-checking-for-nmap"><title>Checking for Nmap and determining its version number</title>
<indexterm><primary><option>--version</option></primary><secondary>example of</secondary></indexterm>
<!--REMEMBER TO UPDATE TEXT BELOW THE SCREENSHOT WHEN I UPDATE THE SCREENSHOT
    TO LATEST VERSION -->
<screen>
felix~&gt; <userinput>nmap --version</userinput>

Nmap version 4.76 ( http://nmap.org )
felix~&gt;
</screen></example>

<para>If Nmap does <emphasis>not</emphasis>
exist on the system (or if your <envar>PATH</envar> is incorrectly
set), an error message such as
<computeroutput>nmap: Command not found</computeroutput> is reported.  As the
example above shows, Nmap responds to the command by printing its
version number (here <literal>4.76</literal>).</para>

<para>Even if your system already has a copy of Nmap, you should
consider upgrading to the latest version available from <ulink
url="http://nmap.org/download.html" />.<indexterm><primary>downloading</primary></indexterm>
Newer versions often run faster, fix important bugs, and feature
updated operating system and service version detection databases.  A
list of changes since the version already on your system can be found
at <ulink url="http://nmap.org/changelog.html" />.<indexterm><primary>changelog</primary></indexterm>
<bookex>
Nmap output examples in this book may not match the output produced by
older versions.
</bookex></para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-interfaces"><title>Command-line and Graphical Interfaces</title>

<para>Nmap has traditionally been a command-line tool run from
a Unix shell or (more recently) Windows command prompt.  This allows
experts to quickly execute a command that does exactly what they want
without having to maneuver through a bunch of configuration panels and
scattered option fields.  This also makes Nmap easier to script and
enables easy sharing of useful commands among the user
community.</para>

<para>One downside of the command-line approach is that it can be
intimidating for new and infrequent users.
Nmap offers more than a hundred
command-line options, although many are obscure features or debugging
controls that most users can ignore.  Many graphical frontends have been
created for those users who prefer a GUI interface.  Nmap has traditionally included a simple GUI for Unix named <application>NmapFE</application><indexterm><primary>NmapFE</primary></indexterm>, but that was replaced in 2007 by Zenmap,
which we have been developing since 2005.  Zenmap is far more powerful and effective than NmapFE, particularly in results viewing.  Zenmap's tab-based interface lets you search and sort
results, and also browse them in several ways (host details, raw Nmap
output, and ports/hosts).  It works on Linux, Windows, Mac
OS X, and other platforms.  Zenmap is covered in depth in <xref linkend="zenmap"/>.  The rest of this book focuses on command-line Nmap invocations.
Once you understand how the
command-line options work and can interpret the output, using Zenmap or
the other available Nmap GUIs is easy.  Nmap's options work the same way
whether you choose them from radio buttons and menus or type them at a
command-line.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-download"><title>Downloading Nmap</title>

<indexterm significance="preferred"><primary>downloading</primary></indexterm>
<para>Nmap.Org is the official source for downloading Nmap source
code and binaries for Nmap and Zenmap.  Source code is distributed in
bzip2 and gzip compressed tar files, and binaries are available for
Linux (RPM format), Windows (NSIS executable installer) and Mac OS X (<filename>.dmg</filename> disk image). Find all of this at <ulink
url="http://nmap.org/download.html" />.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-integrity"><title>Verifying the Integrity of Nmap Downloads</title>

<indexterm><primary>verifying the integrity of downloads</primary></indexterm>
<para>It often pays to be paranoid about the
integrity of files downloaded from the Internet.  Popular packages
such as Sendmail (<ulink
url="http://cert.org/advisories/CA-2002-28.html">example</ulink>),
OpenSSH (<ulink
url="http://cert.org/advisories/CA-2002-24.html">example</ulink>),
tcpdump, Libpcap, BitchX, Fragrouter, and many others have been
infected with malicious trojans.  Software distributions sites at the
Free Software Foundation, Debian, and SourceForge have also been
successfully compromised.  This has never happened to Nmap, but one
should always be careful.  To verify the authenticity of an Nmap
release, consult the PGP detached signatures or cryptographic hashes
(including SHA1 and MD5) posted for the release in the Nmap signatures
directory at <ulink
url="http://nmap.org/dist/sigs/?C=M&amp;O=D"/>.</para>

<para>The most secure verification mechanism is detached PGP<indexterm><primary>PGP signatures</primary></indexterm>
signatures.  As the signing key is never stored on production servers,
even someone who successfully compromises the web server couldn't
forge and properly sign a trojan release.  While numerous applications
are able to verify PGP signatures, I recommend <ulink
url="http://www.gnupg.org/">GNU Privacy Guard (GPG)</ulink>.</para>

<indexterm><primary>keys, cryptographic</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Nmap releases are signed with a special
Nmap Project Signing Key,<indexterm><primary>Nmap Project Signing Key</primary></indexterm>
which can be obtained from the major keyservers or <ulink
url="http://nmap.org/data/nmap_gpgkeys.txt"/>.  My key is
included in that file too.  The keys can be imported with the command
<command>gpg --import nmap_gpgkeys.txt</command>.  You only need to do
this once, then you can verify all future Nmap releases from that
machine.  Before trusting the
keys, verify that the fingerprints match the values shown in <xref
linkend="ex-check-gpg-keys" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>.</para>

<example id="ex-check-gpg-keys">
<title>Verifying the Nmap and Fyodor PGP Key Fingerprints</title>
<screen>
flog~&gt; <userinput>gpg --fingerprint nmap fyodor</userinput>
pub 1024D/33599B5F 2005-04-24
    Key fingerprint = BB61 D057 C0D7 DCEF E730 996C 1AF6 EC50 3359 9B5F
uid                Fyodor &lt;fyodor@insecure.org&gt;
sub 2048g/D3C2241C 2005-04-24

pub 1024D/6B9355D0 2005-04-24
    Key fingerprint = 436D 66AB 9A79 8425 FDA0 E3F8 01AF 9F03 6B93 55D0
uid                Nmap Project Signing Key (http://insecure.org/)
sub 2048g/A50A6A94 2005-04-24
</screen></example>

<para>For every Nmap package download file
(e.g. <filename>nmap-4.76.tar.bz2</filename> and
<filename>nmap-4.76-win32.zip</filename>), there is a corresponding
file in the <filename>sigs</filename> directory with <literal>.asc</literal> appended
to the name (e.g. <filename>nmap-4.76.tar.bz2.asc</filename>).
This is the detached signature file.</para>

<para>With the proper PGP key in your keyring and the detached
signature file downloaded, verifying an Nmap release takes a single
GPG command, as shown in <xref
linkend="ex-gpg-verify-nmap-release-good" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>.  That example assumes that the verified file can be found in the same directory by simply removing <quote>.asc</quote> from the signature filename.  When that isn't the case, simply pass the target filename as the final argument to GPG.  If the file has been
tampered with, the results will look like <xref
linkend="ex-gpg-verify-nmap-release-bad" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>.</para>

<example id="ex-gpg-verify-nmap-release-good">
<title>Verifying PGP key fingerprints (Successful)</title>
<screen>
flog&gt; <userinput>gpg --verify nmap-4.76.tar.bz2.asc </userinput>
gpg: Signature made Fri 12 Sep 2008 02:03:59 AM PDT using DSA key ID 6B9355D0
gpg: Good signature from "Nmap Project Signing Key (http://www.insecure.org/)"
</screen></example>

<example id="ex-gpg-verify-nmap-release-bad">
<title>Detecting a bogus file</title>
<screen>
flog&gt; <userinput>gpg --verify nmap-4.76.tar.bz2.asc nmap-4.76-hacked.tar.bz2</userinput>
gpg: Signature made Fri 12 Sep 2008 02:03:59 AM PDT using DSA key ID 6B9355D0
gpg: BAD signature from "Nmap Project Signing Key (http://www.insecure.org/)"
</screen></example>

<para>While PGP signatures are the recommended validation technique,
SHA2, SHA1, and MD5 (among other)
hashes<indexterm><primary>hashes, cryptographic</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>digests, cryptographic</primary></indexterm>
are made available for more casual
validation.  An attacker who can manipulate your Internet traffic in
real time (and is extremely skilled) or who compromises Nmap.Org
and replaces both the distribution file and digest file, could defeat
this test.  However, it can be useful to check the authoritative
Nmap.Org hashes if you obtain Nmap from a third party or feel it
might have been accidentally corrupted.  For every Nmap package download
file, there is a corresponding file in the <filename>sigs</filename> directory with
<literal>.digest.txt</literal> appended to the name
(e.g. <filename>nmap-4.76.tar.bz2.digest.txt</filename>).  An example
is shown in <xref linkend="ex-digest-file" xrefstyle="select: label nopage" />.  This is the detached
signature file. The hashes from the digest file can be verified using common tools such as
<application>gpg</application>, <application>sha1sum</application>, or <application>md5sum</application>, as shown in <xref
linkend="ex-digest-file-verify" />.</para>

<example id="ex-digest-file">
<title>A typical Nmap release digest file</title>
<screen>
flog&gt; <userinput>cat sigs/nmap-4.76.tgz.digest.txt </userinput>
nmap-4.76.tgz:    MD5 = 54 B5 C9 E3 F4 4C 1A DD  E1 7D F6 81 70 EB 7C FE
nmap-4.76.tgz:   SHA1 = 4374 CF9C A882 2C28 5DE9  D00E 8F67 06D0 BCFA A403
nmap-4.76.tgz: RMD160 = AE7B 80EF 4CE6 DBAA 6E65  76F9 CA38 4A22 3B89 BD3A
nmap-4.76.tgz: SHA224 = 524D479E 717D98D0 2FB0A42B 9A4E6E52 4027C9B6 1D843F95
                        D419F87F
nmap-4.76.tgz: SHA256 = 0E960E05 53EB7647 0C8517A0 038092A3 969DB65C BE23C03F
                        D6DAEF1A CDCC9658
nmap-4.76.tgz: SHA384 = D52917FD 9EE6EE62 F5F456BF E245675D B6EEEBC5 0A287B27
                        3CAA4F50 B171DC23 FE7808A8 C5E3A49A 4A78ACBE A5AEED33
nmap-4.76.tgz: SHA512 = 826CD89F 7930A765 C9FE9B41 1DAFD113 2C883857 2A3A9503
                        E4C1E690 20A37FC8 37564DC3 45FF0C97 EF45ABE6 6CEA49FF
                        E262B403 A52F4ECE C23333A0 48DEDA66
</screen></example>

<example id="ex-digest-file-verify">
<title>Verifying Nmap hashes</title>
<screen>
flog&gt; <userinput>gpg --print-md sha256 nmap-4.76.tgz </userinput>
nmap-4.76.tgz: 0E960E05 53EB7647 0C8517A0 038092A3 969DB65C BE23C03F D6DAEF1A
               CDCC9658
flog&gt; <userinput>sha1sum nmap-4.76.tgz </userinput>
4374cf9ca8822c285de9d00e8f6706d0bcfaa403  nmap-4.76.tgz
flog&gt; <userinput>md5sum nmap-4.76.tgz</userinput>
54b5c9e3f44c1adde17df68170eb7cfe  nmap-4.76.tgz
</screen></example>

<para>While releases from Nmap.Org are signed as described in this
section, certain Nmap add-ons, interfaces, and platform-specific
binaries are developed and distributed by other parties.  They have
different mechanisms for establishing the authenticity of their
downloads.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-svn"><title>Obtaining Nmap from the Subversion (SVN) Repository</title>
<indexterm><primary>Subversion</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>SVN</primary><see>Subversion</see></indexterm>

<para>In addition to regular stable and development releases, the
latest Nmap source code is always available using the <ulink
url="http://subversion.tigris.org">Subversion (SVN) revision control
system</ulink>.  This delivers new features and version/OS detection
database updates immediately as they are developed.  The downside is that
SVN head revisions aren't always as stable as official releases.  So
SVN is most useful for Nmap developers and users who need a fix which
hasn't yet been formally released.</para>

<para>
SVN write access is strictly limited to top Nmap
developers, but everyone has read access to the repository.  Check out
the latest code using the command <command>svn co --username guest
--password "" svn://svn.insecure.org/nmap/</command>.  Then you can later
update your source code by typing <command>svn up</command> in your
working directory.  The <quote>guest</quote> username is required due to an svnserve authorization bug.</para>

<para>While most users only follow the <filename>/nmap</filename>
directory in svn (which pulls
in <filename>/nbase</filename>, <filename>/nsock</filename>,
and <filename>/zenmap</filename> on its own), there is one other
interesting directory: <filename>/nmap-exp</filename>.  This directory
contains <emphasis>experimental</emphasis> Nmap branches which Nmap
developers create when they wish to try new things without
destabilizing Nmap proper.  When developers feel that an experimental
branch is ready for wider-scale testing, they will generally email the
location to the <citetitle>nmap-dev</citetitle> mailing list.</para>

<para>Once Nmap is checked out, you can build it from source code just as you would with the Nmap tarball (described later in this chapter).</para>

<para>If you would like real-time (or digested) notification and diffs by email when any
changes are made to Nmap, sign up for the nmap-svn mailing
list at <ulink
url="http://cgi.insecure.org/mailman/listinfo/nmap-svn"/>.</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="inst-source"><title>Unix Compilation and Installation from Source Code</title> 
<indexterm><primary>Unix, installing on</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Linux</primary><secondary>compiling on</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>installation</primary><secondary>from source code</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>source code</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>compilation</primary></indexterm>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>source code</primary><secondary>advantages of</secondary></indexterm>
While binary packages
(discussed in later sections) are available for most platforms, compilation and
installation from source code is the traditional and most powerful way
to install Nmap.  This ensures that the
latest version is available and allows Nmap
to adapt to the library availability and directory structure of your
system.  For example, Nmap uses the
OpenSSL cryptography libraries for version detection when
available, but most binary packages do not include this
functionality.  On the other hand, binary packages are generally
quicker and easier to install, and allow for consistent management
(installation, removal, upgrading, etc.) of all packaged software on the system.</para>

<para>Source installation is usually a painless process&mdash;the build system is designed to auto-detect as much as possible.  Here are the steps required for a default install:</para>

<orderedlist>

<listitem><para>Download the latest version of Nmap in .tar.bz2 (bzip2 compression) or .tgz (gzip compression) format from <ulink url="http://nmap.org/download.html" />.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Decompress the downloaded tarball with a command such as:</para>

<para><command>bzip2 -cd nmap-<replaceable>VERSION</replaceable>.tar.bz2 | tar xvf -</command></para>

<para>With GNU tar, the simpler command <command>tar xvjf
nmap-<replaceable>VERSION</replaceable>.tar.bz2</command> does the
trick.  If you downloaded the .tgz version, replace
<application>bzip2</application> with <application>gzip</application>
in the decompression command.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Change into the newly created directory: <command>cd nmap-<replaceable>VERSION</replaceable></command></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Configure the build system: <command>./configure</command></para>

<para>If the configuration succeeds, an ASCII art dragon appears to congratulate you on successful configuration and warn you to be careful, as shown in <xref linkend="ex-configure-success" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>.</para>

<example id="ex-configure-success">
<title>Successful configuration screen</title>
<screen>
flog~/nmap> <userinput>./configure</userinput>
<![CDATA[checking build system type... x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu
[hundreds of lines cut]
configure: creating ./config.status
config.status: creating Makefile
config.status: creating nsock_config.h
config.status: nsock_config.h is unchanged
   (  )   /\   _                 (
    \ |  (  \ ( \.(               )                      _____
  \  \ \  `  `   ) \             (  ___                 / _   \
 (_`    \+   . x  ( .\            \/   \____-----------/ (o)   \_
- .-               \+  ;          (  O                           \____
(__                +- .( -'.- <.   \_____________  `              \  /
(_____            ._._: <_ - <- _- _  VVVVVVV VV V\                \/
  .    /./.+-  . .- /  +--  - .    (--_AAAAAAA__A_/                |
  (__ ' /x  / x _/ (                \______________//_              \_______
 , x / ( '  . / .  /                                  \___'          \     /
    /  /  _/ /    +                                       |           \   /
   '  (__/                                               /              \/
                                                       /                  \
             NMAP IS A POWERFUL TOOL -- USE CAREFULLY AND RESPONSIBLY
Configuration complete.  Type make (or gmake on some *BSD machines) to compile.
]]></screen></example>

</listitem>

<listitem><para>Build Nmap (and the Zenmap GUI if its requirements are met):
<command>make</command></para>
<para>Note that GNU Make is required.  On BSD-derived Unix systems,
this is often installed as <emphasis>gmake</emphasis>.  So if
<command>make</command> returns a bunch of errors such as
<quote><literal>Makefile, line 1: Need an
operator</literal></quote>, try running <command>gmake</command> instead.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem><para>Become a privileged user for system-wide install: <command>su root</command></para>

<para>This step may be skipped if you only have an unprivileged shell
account on the system.  In that case, you will likely need to pass
the <option>--prefix</option> option to <literal>configure</literal>
in step four as described in the next section.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem><para>Install Nmap, support files, docs, etc.: <command>make install</command></para>

<para>Congratulations!  Nmap is now installed as <filename>/usr/local/bin/nmap</filename>!  Run it with no arguments for a quick help screen.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>As you can see above, a simple source compilation and install
consists of little more than running <command>./configure;make;make
install</command> as root.  However, there are a number of options available to <application>configure</application> that affect the way Nmap is built.</para>

<sect2 id="inst-configure"><title>Configure Directives</title>

<indexterm><primary>configure directives</primary></indexterm>

<para>Most of the Unix build options are controlled by the <literal>configure</literal> script, as used in step number four above.  There are dozens of command-line parameters and environmental variables which affect the way Nmap is built.  Run <command>./configure --help</command> for a huge list with brief descriptions.  These are not applicable to building Nmap on Windows.  Here are the options which are either specific to Nmap or particularly important:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><option>--prefix=<replaceable>directoryname</replaceable></option></term>

<listitem><para>This option, which is standard to the
<application>configure</application> scripts of most software,
determines where Nmap and its components
are installed.  By default, the prefix is
<filename>/usr/local</filename>, meaning that
<application>nmap</application> is installed in <filename>/usr/local/bin</filename>, the
man page (<filename>nmap.1</filename>) is installed in
<filename>/usr/local/man/man1</filename>, and the data files
(<filename>nmap-os-db</filename>,
<filename>nmap-services</filename>, <filename>nmap-service-probes</filename>,
etc.) are installed under <filename>/usr/local/share/nmap</filename>.
If you only wish to change the path of certain components, use the
options <option>--bindir</option>, <option>--datadir</option>, and/or
<option>--mandir</option>.  An example usage of
<option>--prefix</option> would be to install
Nmap in my account as an unprivileged user.
I would run <command>./configure --prefix=<replaceable>/home/fyodor</replaceable></command>.  Nmap creates subdirectories like <filename>/home/fyodor/man/man1</filename> in the install stage if they do not already exist.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>--without-zenmap</option></term>
<listitem><indexterm><primary>Zenmap</primary><secondary>disabling</secondary></indexterm><para>This option prevents the Zenmap graphical frontend from being installed.  Normally the build system checks your system for requirements such as the Python scripting language and then installs Zenmap if they are all available.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>--with-openssl=<replaceable>directoryname</replaceable></option></term>
<listitem>
<indexterm><primary>OpenSSL</primary><secondary>disabling</secondary></indexterm>
<para>The version detection system and Nmap Scripting Engine are able to probe SSL-encrypted services using the free OpenSSL libraries.  Normally the Nmap build system looks for these libraries on your system and include this capability if they are found.  If they are in a location your compiler does not search for by default, but you still want them to be used, specify <option>--with-openssl=<replaceable>directoryname</replaceable></option>.  Nmap then looks in <replaceable>directoryname</replaceable>/libs for the OpenSSL libraries themselves and <replaceable>directoryname</replaceable>/include for the necessary header files.  Specify <option>--without-openssl</option> to disable SSL entirely.</para>

<indexterm><primary>OpenSSL</primary><secondary>packages required for</secondary></indexterm>
<para>Some distributions ship with user OpenSSL libraries that allow running programs, but not the developer files needed to compile them. Without these developer packages, Nmap will not have OpenSSL support. On Debian-based systems<indexterm><primary>Debian</primary></indexterm>, install the <literal>libssl-dev</literal> package.<indexterm><primary><literal>libssl-dev</literal> package</primary></indexterm> On Red Hat&ndash;based systems,<indexterm><primary>Red Hat</primary></indexterm> install <literal>openssl-devel</literal>.<indexterm><primary><literal>openssl-devel</literal></primary></indexterm>
</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>--with-libpcap=<replaceable>directoryname</replaceable></option></term>
<listitem><para>Nmap uses the <ulink url="http://www.tcpdump.org">Libpcap library</ulink> for capturing raw IP packets.  Nmap normally looks for an existing copy of Libpcap on your system and uses that if the version number and platform is appropriate.  Otherwise Nmap includes its own recent copy of Libpcap, which has been modified for improved Linux functionality.  The specific changes are described in <filename>libpcap/NMAP_MODIFICATIONS</filename> in the Nmap source directory.  Because of these Linux-related changes, Nmap always uses its own Libpcap by default on that platform.  If you wish to force Nmap to link with your own Libpcap, pass the option <option>--with-libpcap=<replaceable>directoryname</replaceable></option> to <application>configure</application>.  Nmap then expects the Libpcap library to be in <filename><replaceable>directoryname</replaceable>/lib/libpcap.a</filename> and the include files to be in <filename><replaceable>directoryname</replaceable>/include</filename>.  Nmap will always use the version of Libpcap included in its tarball if you specify <option>--with-libpcap=included</option>.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>--with-libpcre=<replaceable>directoryname</replaceable></option></term>
<listitem><para>PCRE is a Perl-compatible regular expression library available from <ulink url="http://www.pcre.org" />.  Nmap normally looks for a copy on your system, and then falls back to its own copy if that fails.  If your PCRE library is not in your compiler's standard search path, Nmap probably will not find it.  In that case you can tell Nmap where it can be found by specifying the option <option>--with-libpcre=<replaceable>directoryname</replaceable></option> to <application>configure</application>.  Nmap then expects the library files to be in <filename><replaceable>directoryname</replaceable>/lib</filename> and the include files to be in <filename><replaceable>directoryname</replaceable>/include</filename>.  In some cases, you may wish to use the PCRE libraries included with Nmap in preference to those already on your system.  In that case, specify <option>--with-libpcre=included</option>.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>--with-libdnet=<replaceable>directoryname</replaceable></option></term>
<listitem><para>Libdnet is an excellent networking library that Nmap uses for sending raw ethernet frames. The version in the Nmap tree is heavily modified (particularly the Windows code), so the default is to use that included version.  If you wish to use a version already installed on your system instead, specify <option>--with-libdnet=<replaceable>directoryname</replaceable></option>.  Nmap then expects the library files to be in <filename><replaceable>directoryname</replaceable>/lib</filename> and the include files to be in <filename><replaceable>directoryname</replaceable>/include</filename>.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><literal>--with-localdirs</literal></term>
<listitem><para>This simple option tells Nmap to look in <filename>/usr/local/lib</filename> and <filename>/usr/local/include</filename> for important library and header files.  This should never be necessary, except that some people put such libraries in <filename>/usr/local</filename> without configuring their compiler to find them.  If you are one of those people, use this option.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

</variablelist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-env"><title>Environment Variables</title>

<indexterm><primary>environment variables</primary><secondary>in configuration</secondary></indexterm>

<para>The <filename>configure</filename> script is sensitive to several environment variables. These are some of those variables and their effects.</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<indexterm><primary><envar>CFLAGS</envar></primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary><envar>CXXFLAGS</envar></primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary><envar>LDFLAGS</envar></primary></indexterm>
<envar>CFLAGS</envar></term><term><envar>CXXFLAGS</envar></term><term>LDFLAGS</term>
<listitem><para>Extra options to pass to the C compiler, C++ compiler, and linker, respectively. Because parts of Nmap are written in C and others in C++, it's best to use both <envar>CFLAGS</envar> and <envar>CXXFLAGS</envar> if you're going to use one of them.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<indexterm><primary><envar>LINGUAS</envar> environment variable</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>translations</primary><secondary>of manual pages</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>foreign languages</primary><see>translations</see></indexterm>
<envar>LINGUAS</envar></term>
<listitem><para>By default, <command>make install</command> will install all the available translations of the Nmap man page in addition to the English one. The <envar>LINGUAS</envar> environment variable can control which translations are installed. Its value should be a space-separated list of ISO language codes. For example, to install only the French and German translations, you might run <command>LINGUAS="fr de" make install</command>. To disable the installation of all translations, run configure with the <option>--disable-nls</option> option or set <envar>LINGUAS</envar> to the empty string.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-compilation-probs"><title>If You Encounter Compilation Problems</title>
<indexterm><primary>compilation</primary><secondary>problems with</secondary></indexterm>
<para>In an ideal world, software would always compile perfectly (and quickly) on every system.  Unfortunately, society has not yet reached that state of nirvana.  Despite all our efforts to make Nmap portable, compilation issues occasionally arise.  Here are some suggestions in case the source distribution compilation fails.</para>
<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>Upgrade to the latest Nmap</term>
<listitem><para>Check <ulink url="http://nmap.org/download.html" /> to make sure you are using the latest version of Nmap.  The problem may have already been fixed.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Read the error message carefully</term>
<listitem><para>Scroll up in the output screen and examine the error
messages given when commands fail.  It is often best to find the first
error message, as that often causes a cascade of further errors.  Read
the error message carefully, as it could indicate a system problem
such as low disk space or a broken compiler.  Users with programming
skills may be able to resolve a wider range of problems themselves.
If you make code changes to fix the problem, please send a patch
(created with <command>diff -uw <replaceable>oldfile</replaceable> <replaceable>newfile</replaceable></command>) and any details about your problem and platform to <citetitle>nmap-dev</citetitle> as described in <xref linkend="man-bugs"/>.  Integrating the change into the base Nmap distribution allows many other users to benefit, and prevents you from having to make the changes with each new Nmap version.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Ask Google and other Internet resources</term>
<listitem><para>Try searching for the exact error message on Google or other search engines.  You might also want to browse recent activity on the Nmap development
(<citetitle>nmap-dev</citetitle>)<indexterm><primary><citetitle>nmap-dev</citetitle> mailing list</primary></indexterm>
list&mdash;archives and a search interface are available at <ulink url="http://seclists.org" />.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Ask <citetitle>nmap-dev</citetitle></term>
<listitem><para>If none of your research leads to a solution, try
sending a report to the Nmap development
(<citetitle>nmap-dev</citetitle>) mailing list, as described in
<xref linkend="man-bugs"/>.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Consider binary packages</term>
<listitem>
<indexterm><primary>binary packages</primary></indexterm>
<para>Binary packages of Nmap are available on most platforms and are
usually easy to install.  The downsides are that they may not be as
up-to-date and you lose some of the flexibility of self-compilation.
Later sections of this chapter describe how to find binary packages on
many platforms, and even more are available via Internet searching.
Obviously you should only install binary packages from reputable
sources.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="inst-linux"><title>Linux Distributions</title>

<para>
Linux is the most popular platform for running Nmap.  In one user
survey, 86% said that Linux was at least one of the platforms on which
they run Nmap.  The first release of Nmap in
1997 <emphasis>only</emphasis> ran on Linux.</para>

<para>Linux users can choose between a source code install or using
binary packages provided by their distribution or Insecure.Org.  The
binary packages are generally quicker and easier to install, and are
often slightly customized to use the distribution's standard directory
paths and such.  These packages also allow for consistent management
in terms of upgrading, removing, or surveying software on the system.
A downside is that packages created by the distributions are
necessarily behind the Nmap.Org source releases.  Most Linux
distributions keep their Nmap package
relatively current, though a few are way out of date.  Choosing the
source install allows for more flexibility in determining how Nmap is
built and optimized for your system.  To build Nmap from source, see
<xref linkend="inst-source" />.  Here are simple package instructions
for the most common distributions.</para>

<sect2 id="inst-rpm"><title>RPM-based Distributions (Red Hat, Mandrake, SUSE, Fedora)</title>
<indexterm><primary>RPM</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Linux</primary><secondary>installing on, with RPM</secondary>></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Red Hat (Linux distribution)</primary><secondary>installing on, with RPM</secondary>></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Mandrake (Linux distribution)</primary><secondary>installing on, with RPM</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>SUSE (Linux distribution)</primary><secondary>installing on, with RPM</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Fedora (Linux distribution)</primary><secondary>installing on, with RPM</secondary></indexterm>

<para>I build RPM packages for every release of Nmap and post them to
the Nmap download page at <ulink url="http://nmap.org/download.html" />.
I build two packages:  The <literal>nmap</literal> package contains
just the command-line executable and data files, while the
<literal>zenmap</literal> package contains the optional <application>Zenmap</application>
graphical frontend (see <xref linkend="zenmap"/>).
The <literal>zenmap</literal> package requires
that the <literal>nmap</literal> package be installed first.  One down
side to installing the RPMs rather than compiling from source is that
the RPMs don't support OpenSSL for version detection and Nmap Scripting Engine probing of SSL services.</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>RPM</primary><secondary>installing from</secondary></indexterm>
Installing via <application>RPM</application> is quite easy&mdash;it
even downloads the package for you when given the proper URLs.  The following example downloads and installs Nmap 4.68, including the frontend.  Of course you should use the latest version at the download site above instead.  Any existing RPM-installed versions are
upgraded. <xref linkend="ex-nmap-install-from-rpms" xrefstyle="select: label nopage" /> demonstrates this installation process.</para>

<example id="ex-nmap-install-from-rpms"><title>Installing Nmap from binary RPMs</title>
<screen>
# <userinput>rpm -vhU http://nmap.org/dist/nmap-4.68-1.i386.rpm</userinput>
Retrieving http://nmap.org/dist/nmap-4.68-1.i386.rpm
Preparing...                ########################################### [100%]
   1:nmap                   ########################################### [100%]
# <userinput>rpm -vhU http://nmap.org/dist/zenmap-4.68-1.noarch.rpm</userinput>
Retrieving http://nmap.org/dist/zenmap-4.68-1.noarch.rpm
Preparing...                ########################################### [100%]
   1:zenmap                 ########################################### [100%]
</screen>
</example>

<para>As the filenames above imply, these binary RPMs were created for normal PCs (x86 architecture).<indexterm><primary>x86 architecture</primary></indexterm>  I also distribute x86_64<indexterm><primary>x86_64 architecture</primary></indexterm> binaries for 64-bit Linux users.  These binaries won't work for the relatively few Linux users on other platforms such as SPARC, Alpha, or PowerPC.  They also may refuse to install if your library versions are sufficiently different from what the RPMs were initially built on.  One option in these cases would be to find binary RPMs prepared by your Linux vendor for your specific distribution.  The original install CDs or DVD are a good place to start.  Unfortunately, those may not be current or available.  Another option is to install Nmap from source code as described previously, though you lose the binary package maintenance consistency benefits.  A third option is to build and install your own binary RPMs from the source RPMs distributed from the download page above.  <xref linkend="ex-nmap-install-from-srpms" xrefstyle="select: label nopage" /> demonstrates this technique with Nmap 4.68.</para>

<example id="ex-nmap-install-from-srpms"><title>Building and installing Nmap from source RPMs</title>
<screen>
&gt; <userinput>rpmbuild --rebuild http://nmap.org/dist/nmap-4.68-1.src.rpm</userinput>
[ hundreds of lines cut ]
Wrote: /home/fyodor/rpmdir/RPMS/i386/nmap-4.68-1.i386.rpm
[ cut ]
&gt; <userinput>su</userinput>
Password: 
# <userinput>rpm -vhU /home/fyodor/rpmdir/RPMS/i386/nmap-4.68-1.i386.rpm</userinput>
Preparing...                ########################################### [100%]
   1:nmap                   ########################################### [100%]
#
</screen>
</example>

<para>It is not necessary to rebuild Zenmap in this fashion because the
Zenmap RPM is architecture-independent (<quote>noarch</quote>). For that
reason there are no Zenmap source RPMs.</para>

<para>Removing RPM packages is as easy as <command>rpm -e nmap zenmap</command>.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-yum"><title>Updating Red Hat, Fedora, Mandrake, and Yellow Dog Linux with Yum</title>
<indexterm><primary>Yum</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Linux</primary><secondary>installing on, with Yum</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Red Hat (Linux distribution)</primary><secondary>installing on, with Yum</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Mandrake (Linux distribution)</primary><secondary>installing on, with Yum</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Yellow Dog (Linux distribution)</primary><secondary>installing on, with Yum</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Fedora (Linux distribution)</primary><secondary>installing on, with Yum</secondary></indexterm>

<para>The Red Hat, Fedora, Mandrake, and Yellow Dog Linux
distributions have an application named <application>Yum</application>
which manages software installation and updates from central RPM
repositories.  This makes software installation and updates trivial.
Since distribution-specific Yum repositories are normally used, you
know the software has already been tested for compatibility with your
particular distribution.  Most distributions do maintain Nmap in their
Yum repository, but they don't always keep it up to date.  This is
particularly problematic if you (like most people) don't always
quickly update to the latest release of your distribution.  If you are
running a two-year old Linux release, Yum will often give you a
two-year-old version of Nmap.  Even the latest version of
distributions often take months to update to a new Nmap release.  So
for the latest version of Nmap on these systems, try the RPMs we
distribute as described in the previous section.  But if our
RPMs aren't compatible with your system or you are in a great hurry,
installing Nmap from Yum is usually as simple as executing
<command>yum install nmap</command> (run <command>yum install nmap zenmap</command>
if you would like the GUI too, though some distributions don't yet package Zenmap).  Yum takes care of contacting a
repository on the Internet, finding the appropriate package for
your architecture, and then installing it along with any necessary
dependencies.  This is shown (edited for brevity) in <xref
linkend="ex-nmap-install-from-yum" xrefstyle="select: label nopage" />.  You can later perform
<command>yum update</command> to install available updates to Nmap and other
packages in the repository.</para>

<example id="ex-nmap-install-from-yum"><title>Installing Nmap from a system Yum repository</title>
<screen>
flog~# <userinput>yum install nmap</userinput>
<![CDATA[Setting up Install Process
Parsing package install arguments
Resolving Dependencies
--> Running transaction check
---> Package nmap.x86_64 2:4.52-1.fc8 set to be updated
--> Finished Dependency Resolution
Dependencies Resolved
=============================================================================
 Package                 Arch       Version          Repository        Size 
=============================================================================
Installing:
 nmap                    x86_64     2:4.52-1.fc8     updates           1.0 M

Transaction Summary
=============================================================================
Install      1 Package(s)         
Update       0 Package(s)         
Remove       0 Package(s)         

Total download size: 1.0 M
Is this ok [y/N]: y
Downloading Packages:
(1/1): nmap-4.52-1.fc8.x8 100% |=========================| 1.0 MB    00:02     
Running Transaction Test
Transaction Test Succeeded
Running Transaction
  Installing: nmap                         ######################### [1/1] 

Installed: nmap.x86_64 2:4.52-1.fc8
Complete!
]]></screen>
</example>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-debian"><title>Debian Linux and Derivatives such as Ubuntu</title>
<indexterm><primary>Linux</primary><secondary>installing on, with <application>apt-get</application></secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Debian, installing on</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Ubuntu, installing on</primary></indexterm>
<para>LaMont Jones
<indexterm><primary>Jones, LaMont</primary></indexterm>
maintaining the Nmap <literal>deb</literal>
packages, including keeping them reasonably up-to-date.  The proper
upgrade/install command is <command>apt-get install nmap</command>.
<indexterm><primary><application>apt-get</application></primary></indexterm>
This works for Debian derivatives such as Ubuntu too.  Information on
the latest Debian <quote>stable</quote> Nmap package is available at <ulink
url="http://packages.debian.org/stable/nmap" /> and the
development (<quote>unstable</quote>) Nmap and Zenmap packages are available from <ulink
url="http://packages.debian.org/unstable/nmap" /> and <ulink url="http://packages.debian.org/unstable/zenmap"/>.</para>

<para>Sometimes Debian's Nmap releases are a year or more behind the current Nmap version.  One option for obtaining the latest release is to compile from source code, as described in <xref linkend="inst-source"/>.  Another option is to download the RPM-format binaries from the Nmap download page, convert them to <literal>deb</literal> packages using the <application>alien</application> command, and then install them using <application>dpkg</application>, as described in the following list:</para>

<orderedlist id="install-list-deb">
<title>Steps for converting Nmap RPM files to Debian/Ubuntu <filename>deb</filename> format for installation on Debian/Ubuntu</title>
<listitem><para>If you don't have the <application>alien</application> command, install it with a command such as <command>sudo apt-get install alien</command></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Download the Nmap RPMs for your platform (x86 or x86-64) from <ulink url="http://nmap.org/download.html"/>.  This description will use <filename>nmap-5.21-1.x86_64.rpm</filename></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Verify the download integrity as described in <xref linkend="inst-integrity"/>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Generate a Debian package with a command such as <command>sudo alien nmap-5.21-1.x86_64.rpm</command></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Install the Debian package with a command such as <command>sudo dpkg --install nmap_5.21-2_amd64.deb</command></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Steps 2&ndash;5 can be repeated for the other Nmap RPMs such as Zenmap, Ncat, and Nping.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-linux-other"><title>Other Linux Distributions</title>
<para>There are far too many Linux distributions available to list
here, but even many of the obscure ones include Nmap in their package
tree.  If they don't, you can simply compile from source code as
described in <xref linkend="inst-source" />.
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="inst-windows"><title>Windows</title>
<indexterm class="startofrange" id="inst-windows-indexterm"><primary>Windows</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Microsoft Windows</primary><see>Windows</see></indexterm>

<para>While Nmap was once a Unix-only tool, a Windows version was
released in 2000 and has since become the second most popular Nmap
platform (behind Linux). Because of this popularity and the fact that
many Windows users do not have a compiler, binary executables are
distributed for each major Nmap release.  Nmap supports Windows 7,
Windows Server 2008 and 2003, Windows Vista, and Windows XP SP1 and
later.  We also have a <ulink
url="https://secwiki.org/w/Nmap_On_Old_Windows_Releases">help
page</ulink> for users who must run Nmap on earlier versions of
Windows.  While it has improved dramatically, the Windows port is not
quite as efficient as on Unix.  Here are the known limitations:
</para>

<indexterm><primary>Windows</primary><secondary>limitations of</secondary></indexterm>
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>You cannot generally scan your own machine from itself
(using a loopback<indexterm><primary>loopback
interface</primary></indexterm> IP such as 127.0.0.1 or any of its
registered IP addresses).  This is a Windows limitation that we
haven't yet worked around.  If you really want to do this, use a TCP
connect scan without pinging (<option>-sT -Pn</option>) as that uses
the high level socket API rather than sending raw
packets.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Nmap only supports ethernet interfaces (including most
802.11 wireless cards and many VPN clients) for raw packet scans.
Unless you use the <option>-sT -Pn</option> options, RAS connections
(such as PPP dialups) and certain VPN clients are not supported.  This
support was dropped when Microsoft removed raw TCP/IP socket support
in Windows XP SP2.  Now Nmap must send lower-level ethernet frames
instead.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<indexterm><primary>Windows</primary><secondary>performance of</secondary></indexterm>
<para>Scans speeds on Windows are generally comparable to those on
Unix, though the latter often has a slight performance edge.  One
exception to this is connect scan (<option>-sT</option>), which is
often much slower on Windows because of deficiencies in the Windows
networking API.  This is a shame, since that is the one TCP scan that
works against localhost and over all networking types (not just
ethernet, like the raw packet scans).  Connect scan performance can be
improved substantially by applying the Registry changes in the
<filename>nmap_performance.reg</filename> file included with Nmap.  By default these changes are applied for you by the Nmap executable installer.  This registry file
is in the <filename>nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable></filename>
directory of the Windows binary zip file, and
<filename>nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>/mswin32</filename>
in the source tarball (where <replaceable>version</replaceable> is the
version number of the specific release).  These changes increase
the number of ephemeral ports reserved for user applications (such as
Nmap) and reduce the time delay before a closed connection can
be reused.  Most people simply check the box to apply these changes in the executable Nmap installer, but you can also apply them by double-clicking on
<filename>nmap_performance.reg</filename>, or by running the command
<command>regedt32 nmap_performance.reg</command>.  To make the changes by hand, add these three Registry DWORD values to
<literal>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Services\Tcpip\Parameters</literal>:</para>

<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term>MaxUserPort</term>
     <listitem><para>Set a large value such as 65534 (0x0000fffe).  See <ulink url="http://support.microsoft.com/kb/Q196271">MS KB Q196271</ulink>.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>TCPTimedWaitDelay</term>
     <listitem><para>Set the minimum value (0x0000001e). See <ulink url="http://support.microsoft.com/kb/Q149532">MS KB Q149532</ulink>.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>StrictTimeWaitSeqCheck</term>
     <listitem><para>Set to 1 so TCPTimedWaitDelay is checked.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<note><para>I would like to thank Ryan Permeh<indexterm><primary>Permeh, Ryan</primary></indexterm> of eEye, Andy Lutomirski<indexterm><primary>Lutomirski, Andy</primary></indexterm>, and
  Jens Vogt<indexterm><primary>Vogt, Jens</primary></indexterm> for their hard work on the Nmap Windows port.  For many
  years, Nmap was a Unix-only tool, and it would likely still be that
  way if not for their efforts.</para></note>

<para>Windows users have three choices for installing
Nmap, all of which are available from the
download page at <ulink url="http://nmap.org/download.html" />.</para>

<sect2 id="inst-win-exe"><title>Windows Self-installer</title>
<indexterm><primary>Windows</primary><secondary>self-installer</secondary></indexterm>

<para>Every Nmap release includes a Windows
self-installer named
<filename>nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>-setup.exe</filename>
(where <replaceable>version</replaceable> is the version number of the
specific release).  Most Nmap users choose this option since it is so
easy.  Another advantage of the self-installer is that it provides the option to install the Zenmap GUI and other tools.  Simply run the installer file and let it walk you through
panels for choosing an install path and installing WinPcap.  The
installer was created with the open-source <ulink
url="http://nsis.sourceforge.net/Main_Page">Nullsoft Scriptable
Install System</ulink>.  After it completes, read <xref
linkend="inst-win-exec"/> for instructions on executing Nmap on the
command-line or through Zenmap.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-win-zip"><title>Command-line Zip Binaries</title>
<indexterm><primary>Windows</primary><secondary>zip binaries</secondary></indexterm>

<note><para>Most users prefer installing Nmap with the self-installer discussed previously.</para></note>

<para>Every stable Nmap release comes with Windows
command-line binaries and associated files in a Zip archive.  No
graphical interface is included, so you need to run
<literal>nmap.exe</literal> from a DOS/command window.  Or you can
download and install a superior command shell such as those included
with the free
Cygwin<indexterm><primary>Cygwin</primary></indexterm>
system available from <ulink url="http://www.cygwin.com" />.  Here are the step-by-step instructions for installing and executing the Nmap .zip binaries.</para>

<sect3 id="inst-win-zip-install"><title>Installing the Nmap zip binaries</title>
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>Download the .zip binaries from <ulink url="http://nmap.org/download.html" />.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Uncompress the zip file into the directory you want
Nmap to reside in.  An example would be <filename>C:\Program
Files</filename>.  A directory called
<filename>nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable></filename> should be created, which includes
the Nmap executable and data files.  Microsoft Windows XP and Vista
include zip extraction&mdash;just right-click on the file in
<application>Explorer</application>.  If you do not have a Zip
decompression program, there is one (called unzip) in Cygwin described
above, or you can download the open-source and free <ulink
url="http://www.7-zip.org">7-Zip utility</ulink>.  Commercial
alternatives are <ulink url="http://www.winzip.com">WinZip</ulink> and
<ulink url="http://www.pkware.com">PKZIP</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>For improved performance, apply the Nmap Registry
changes discussed previously.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Nmap requires the free WinPcap packet capture library.
We build our own WinPcap installer which is available in the zip file
as <filename>winpcap-nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.exe</filename>,
where <replaceable>version</replaceable> is the WinPcap version rather
than the Nmap version.  Alternatively, you can obtain and install
the latest version from <ulink url="http://www.winpcap.org" />.  You
must install version 4.0 or later.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Due to the way Nmap is compiled, it requires the
<ulink role="hidepdf" url="http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?familyid=2051a0c1-c9b5-4b0a-a8f5-770a549fd78c&amp;displaylang=en">Microsoft Visual C++ 2008 Redistributable Package</ulink> of runtime
components. Many systems already have this installed from other
packages, but you should run <filename>vcredist_x86.exe</filename>
from the zip file just in case you need it. Pass the <option>/q</option> option to run that installer in quiet (non interactive) mode.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Instructions for executing your compiled Nmap are
given in <xref linkend="inst-win-exec"/>.</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-win-source"><title>Compile from Source Code</title>
<indexterm><primary>Windows</primary><secondary>compiling on</secondary></indexterm>

<para>Most Windows users prefer to use the Nmap binary self-installer,
but compilation from source code is an option, particularly if you plan to help with Nmap development.  Compilation requires
Microsoft Visual C++ 2010, which is part of their commercial Visual Studio suite.  Any of the Visual Studio 2010 editions should work, including the free <ulink
url="http://www.microsoft.com/express/Windows/">Visual C++ 2010 Express SP1</ulink>.</para>

<orderedlist id="nmap-install-windows-compile-from-source"><title>Compiling Nmap on Windows from Source</title>

<listitem><para>Decide whether to obtain the Nmap source code by downloading the latest release from nmap.org, or using a Subversion client to retrieve even newer (but less tested) code from our repository.  These instructions are for the web download approach, but using Subversion instead is straightforward (see <xref linkend="inst-svn"/>).</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Download the latest Nmap source distribution from <ulink url="http://nmap.org/download.html" />.  It has the name
<filename>nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.tar.bz2</filename> or
<filename>nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.tgz</filename>.  Those are the same tar file compressed using bzip2 or gzip, respectively.  The bzip2-compressed version is smaller.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Uncompress the source code file you just downloaded.  Recent releases of the free <ulink url="http://www.cygwin.com/">Cygwin distribution</ulink><indexterm><primary>Cygwin</primary></indexterm> can handle both the <filename>.tar.bz2</filename> and <literal>.tgz</literal> formats.  Use the command <command>tar xvjf nmap-version.tar.bz2</command> or <command>tar xvzf nmap-version.tgz</command>, respectively.  Alternatively, the common <application>WinZip</application> application can decompress these files.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Open Visual Studio and the Nmap solution file (<filename>nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>/mswin32/nmap.sln</filename>).</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Right click on <literal>Solution 'nmap'</literal> in the Solution Explorer sidebar and choose <guimenuitem>Configuration Manager</guimenuitem>.  Ensure that the active solution configuration is <literal>Release</literal> and then close the Configuration Manager.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Build Nmap by pressing <keycap>F7</keycap> or choosing <guimenuitem>Build
Solution</guimenuitem> from the GUI.  Nmap should begin compiling, and
end with the line <quote><literal>-- Done --</literal></quote> saying
that all projects built successfully and there were zero
failures.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The executable and data files can be found in <filename>nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>/mswin32/Release/</filename>.  You can copy them to a preferred directory as long as they are all kept together.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ensure that you have WinPcap installed.  You can obtain it by installing our binary self-installer or executing <filename>winpcap-nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.exe</filename> from our zip package.  Alternatively, you can obtain the official installer at <ulink url="http://www.winpcap.org"/>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Instructions for executing your compiled Nmap are
given in the next section.</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

<para>If you wish to build an Nmap executable Windows
installer or Zenmap executable,
see <filename>docs/win32-installer-zenmap-buildguide.txt</filename> in
Nmap SVN
(also <ulink url="http://nmap.org/data/win32-installer-zenmap-buildguide.txt">available
on the Nmap Web site</ulink>).</para>

<para>Many people have asked whether Nmap can be compiled with the
<application>gcc</application>/<application>g++</application> included
with Cygwin or other compilers.  Some users have reported success with
this, but we don't maintain instructions for building Nmap under
Cygwin.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-win-exec"><title>Executing Nmap on Windows</title>
<indexterm><primary>Windows</primary><secondary>running Nmap on</secondary></indexterm>

<para>Nmap releases now include the
<application>Zenmap</application> graphical user interface for Nmap.
If you used the Nmap installer and left the Zenmap field checked,
there should be a new Zenmap entry on your desktop and Start Menu.
Click this to get started.  Zenmap is fully documented in
<xref linkend="zenmap"/>.  While many users love Zenmap, others prefer
the traditional command-line approach to executing Nmap.  Here are
detailed instructions for users who are unfamiliar with command-line
interfaces:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>Make sure the user you are logged in as has
administrative privileges<indexterm><primary>privileged users</primary></indexterm>
on the computer (user should be a member of the <literal>administrators</literal> group).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Open a command/DOS Window.  Though it can be found in
the program menu tree, the simplest approach is to choose <guimenu>Start</guimenu> 
-> <guimenuitem>Run</guimenuitem> and type <command>cmd&lt;enter&gt;</command>.  Opening a Cygwin window (if you installed it) by clicking on the Cygwin icon on the desktop works too, although the necessary commands differ slightly from those shown here.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Change to the directory you installed Nmap into.  You can skip this step if Nmap is already in your command path (the Zenmap isntaller adds it there by default).  Otherwise, type the following commands.</para>
<screen>
<userinput>c:</userinput>
<userinput>cd "\Program Files (x86)\Nmap"</userinput>
</screen>

<para>On Windows releases prior to Windows 7, specify <filename>\Program Files\Nmap</filename> instead. The directory will also be different if you chose to install Nmap in a non-default location.</para>

</listitem>
<listitem><para>Execute <command>nmap.exe</command>.  <xref linkend="fig-windows-cmdshell-exec" xrefstyle="select: label nopage" /> is a screen shot showing a simple example.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<figure id="fig-windows-cmdshell-exec"><title>Executing Nmap from a Windows command shell</title>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
<web>
    <imagedata fileref="images/nmap-windows-demo-669x326.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="669" contentdepth="326" />
</web>
<print>
    <imagedata fileref="images/nmap-windows-demo-669x326.png" format="PNG" scale="50" />
</print>
  </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>If you execute Nmap frequently, you can add the Nmap directory
(<filename>c:\Program Files (x86)\Nmap</filename> by default on
Windows 7) to your command execution path.  The exact place
to set this varies by Windows platform.  On my Windows XP box, which
installs Nmap in <filename>c:\Program Files\Nmap</filename>, I do the
following:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>From the desktop, right click on <literal>My
Computer</literal> and then click <guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>In the System Properties window, click the
<guimenuitem>Advanced</guimenuitem> tab.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Click the <guimenuitem>Environment
Variables</guimenuitem> button.</para></listitem>

<listitem>
<indexterm><primary><envar>PATH</envar> environment variable</primary><secondary><envar>Path</envar> on Windows</secondary></indexterm>
<para>
Choose <literal>Path</literal> from the
<literal>System variables</literal> section, then hit
edit.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Add a semi-colon and then your Nmap directory (e.g. <filename>c:\Program Files\Nmap</filename>) to the end of the value.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Open a new DOS window and you should be able to execute a
command such as <command>nmap scanme.nmap.org</command> from any directory.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

</sect2>

<indexterm class="endofrange" startref="inst-windows-indexterm"/>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="inst-solaris"><title>Sun Solaris</title>
<indexterm><primary>Solaris, installing on</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Sun Solaris</primary><see>Solaris</see></indexterm>

<para>Solaris has long been well-supported by Nmap.  Sun even donated a complete SPARCstation to the project, which is still being used to test new Nmap builds.  For this reason, many Solaris users compile and install from source code as described in <xref linkend="inst-source" />.</para>

<para>Users who prefer native Solaris packages will be pleased to
learn that
Steven Christensen<indexterm><primary>Christensen, Steven</primary></indexterm>
does an excellent job of maintaining
Nmap packages at <ulink url="http://www.sunfreeware.com" /> for all modern Solaris versions and architectures.  Instructions are
on his site, and are generally very simple: download the
appropriate Nmap package for your version
of Solaris, decompress it, and then run <command>pkgadd -d <replaceable>packagename</replaceable></command>.
As is generally the case with contributed binary packages, these
Solaris packages are simple and quick to install.  The advantages of
compiling from source are that a newer version may be available and
you have more flexibility in the build process.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="inst-macosx"><title>Apple Mac OS X</title>
<indexterm class="startofrange" id="inst-macosx-indexterm"><primary>Mac OS X</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Apple Mac OS X</primary><see>Mac OS X</see></indexterm>

<para>Thanks to several people graciously donating shell accounts on
their Mac OS X boxes, Nmap usually compiles on that platform without
problems. Because not everyone has the development tools necessary to
compile from source, there is an executable installer as well.  Nmap
is also available through systems such as MacPorts and Fink which
package Unix software for Mac OS X.</para>

<sect2 id="inst-macosx-installer">
<title>Executable Installer</title>
<indexterm><primary>Mac OS X</primary><secondary>executable installer</secondary></indexterm>

<para>The easiest way to install Nmap and Zenmap on Mac OS X is to use
our installer. The
<ulink url="http://nmap.org/download.html#macosx">Mac OS X section of
the Nmap download page</ulink> provides a file named
<filename>nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.dmg</filename>, where
<replaceable>version</replaceable> is the version number of the most
recent release. The
<filename>.dmg</filename><indexterm><primary sortas="dmg (Mac OS X disk image)"><filename>.dmg</filename> (Mac OS X disk image)</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>disk image (Mac OS X)</primary></indexterm>
file is known as a
<quote>disk image</quote>. Installation instructions follow:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>Download the file
<filename>nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.dmg</filename>.
Double-click the icon to open it. (Depending on how you downloaded the
file, it may be opened automatically.)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The contents of the disk image will be displayed. One of
the files will be a Mac meta-package file named
<filename>nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.mpkg</filename>.
Double-click it to start the installer.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Follow the instructions in the
installer. You will be asked for your password since Nmap installs in a system directory.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Once the installer is finished, eject the disk image by
control-clicking on its icon and selecting
<guimenuitem>Eject</guimenuitem>. The disk image may now be placed in
the trash.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>See the instructions in <xref linkend="inst-macosx-exec"/> for
help on running Nmap and Zenmap after they are installed.</para>

<para>The programs installed by the installer are universal binaries
that will run on Mac OS X 10.4 (Tiger) or later. Users of earlier versions will
have to compile from source or use a third-party package.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-macosx-source">
<indexterm><primary>Mac OS X</primary><secondary>compiling on</secondary></indexterm>
<title>Compile from Source Code</title>

<para>Compiling Nmap from source on Mac OS X is no more difficult than
on other platforms once a proper build environment is in place.</para>

<sect3>
<title>Compile Nmap from source code</title>

<para>Compiling Nmap on Mac OS X requires
<ulink url="http://developer.apple.com/tools/xcode/">Xcode</ulink>,<indexterm><primary>Xcode</primary></indexterm>
Apple's developer tools that include GCC and the rest of the usual build
system. Xcode is not installed by default, but is available as an
optional install on the Mac OS X installation discs. If you do not have
the installation discs or if you want a newer version, you can download
Xcode free of charge by following these steps.</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>Apple restricts downloads of Xcode to members of the
Apple Developer Connection.<indexterm><primary>Apple Developer Connection</primary></indexterm>
Browse to
<ulink url="http://connect.apple.com" /> and fill out some forms to
create an account. Skip to the next step if you already have an
account.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Return to <ulink url="http://connect.apple.com" /> and
log in with your account credentials.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Hit the <literal>Download</literal> link and then choose
<literal>Developer Tools</literal>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Download and install the most recent
<literal>Xcode</literal>.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>These exact steps may change, but it is hoped that this general
approach will continue to work.</para>

<para>Once you have installed Xcode, follow the compilation instructions found in <xref linkend="inst-source" />.  Note that on some older versions of Mac OS X, you may have to replace the command <command>./configure</command> with <command>./configure CPP=/usr/bin/cpp</command>.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Compile Zenmap from source code</title>

<indexterm><primary>Zenmap</primary><secondary>dependencies of</secondary></indexterm>
<para>Zenmap depends on some external libraries that do not come with
Mac OS X, including GTK+ and PyGTK. These libraries have many dependencies
of their own. A convenient way to install all of them is to use a
third-party packaging system as described in
<xref linkend="inst-macosx-third-party" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>. Once the dependencies are
installed, follow the instructions in <xref linkend="inst-source"/> to
install Zenmap as usual.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-macosx-third-party">
<indexterm><primary>Mac OS X</primary><secondary>installing from third-party packages</secondary></indexterm>
<title>Third-party Packages</title>

<para>Another option for installing Nmap is to use a system
which packages Unix software for Mac OS X. The two discussed here are
<ulink url="http://www.finkproject.org">Fink</ulink> and
<ulink url="http://www.macports.org">MacPorts</ulink>. See the
respective projects' web sites for how to install the package
managers.</para>

<indexterm><primary>Fink</primary></indexterm>
<para>To install using Fink, run the command <command>fink install
nmap</command>. Nmap will be installed as
<filename>/sw/bin/nmap</filename>. To uninstall use the command
<command>fink remove nmap</command>.</para>

<indexterm><primary>MacPorts</primary></indexterm>
<para>To install using MacPorts, run <command>sudo port
install nmap</command>. Nmap will be installed as
<filename>/opt/local/bin/nmap</filename>. To uninstall, run
<command>sudo port uninstall nmap</command>.</para>

<para>These systems install the <filename>nmap</filename>
executable outside the global <envar>PATH</envar>. To enable Zenmap to
find it, set the <varname>nmap_command_path</varname> variable in
<filename>zenmap.conf</filename> to <filename>/sw/bin/nmap</filename> or
<filename>/opt/local/bin/nmap</filename> as described in
<xref linkend="zenmap-executable"/>.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-macosx-exec">
<indexterm><primary>Mac OS X</primary><secondary>running Nmap on</secondary></indexterm>
<title>Executing Nmap on Mac OS X</title>

<para>The terminal emulator in Mac OS X is called
<application>Terminal</application>, and is located in the directory
<filename>/Applications/Utilities</filename>. Open it and a
terminal window appears. This is where you will type your commands.</para>

<para>
By default the root user is disabled on Mac OS X. To run a scan with
root privileges prefix the command name with
<application>sudo</application>,<indexterm><primary><application>sudo</application></primary></indexterm>
as
in <command>sudo nmap -sS <replaceable>target</replaceable></command>.
You will be asked for a password, which is just your normal login
password. Only users with administrator privileges can do this.</para>

<para>Zenmap requires the <application>X11</application> application to
be installed. If it was not installed by default it may be available as
an optional install on the Mac OS X installation discs.</para>

<para>When Zenmap is started, a dialog is displayed requesting that you
type your password. Users with
administrator privileges<indexterm><primary>privileged users</primary></indexterm>
may enter their
password to allow Zenmap to run as the root user and run more advanced
scans. To run Zenmap in unprivileged mode, select the
<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button on this authentication dialog.</para>
</sect2>

<indexterm class="endofrange" startref="inst-macosx-indexterm"/>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="inst-bsd"><title>FreeBSD / OpenBSD / NetBSD</title>
<indexterm><primary>BSDs</primary></indexterm>


<para>The BSD flavors are well supported by Nmap, so you can simply
compile it from source as described in <xref linkend="inst-source"
/>.  This provides the normal advantages of always having the latest
version and a flexible build process.  If you prefer binary packages,
these *BSD variants each maintain their own Nmap packages.  Many BSD
systems also have a <emphasis>ports tree</emphasis> which standardizes the compilation of
popular applications.   Instructions for installing Nmap on
the most popular *BSD variants follow.</para>

<sect2 id="inst-openbsd"><title>OpenBSD Binary Packages and Source Ports Instructions</title>
<indexterm><primary>OpenBSD, installing on</primary></indexterm>

<para>According to the <ulink
url="http://www.openbsd.org/faq/">OpenBSD FAQ</ulink>, users
<quote>are HIGHLY advised to use packages over building an application
from ports. The OpenBSD ports team considers packages to be the goal
of their porting work, not the ports themselves.</quote>  That same
FAQ contains detailed instructions for each method.  Here is a summary:</para>

<orderedlist><title>Installation using binary packages</title>
<listitem><para>Choose a mirror from <ulink
url="http://www.openbsd.org/ftp.html" />, then FTP in and grab the Nmap
package from
<filename>/pub/OpenBSD/<replaceable>version</replaceable>/packages/<replaceable>platform</replaceable>/nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.tgz</filename>.
Or obtain it from the OpenBSD distribution CD-ROM.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>As root, execute: <command>pkg_add -v nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.tgz</command></para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<orderedlist><title>Installation using the source ports tree</title>
<listitem><para>If you do not already have a copy of the ports tree, obtain it via CVS using instructions at <ulink url="http://openbsd.org/faq/faq15.html" />.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>As root, execute the following command (replace <filename>/usr/ports</filename> with your local ports directory if it differs):</para>
<para><command>cd /usr/ports/net/nmap &amp;&amp; make install clean</command></para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-freebsd"><title>FreeBSD Binary Package and Source Ports Instructions</title>
<indexterm><primary>FreeBSD, installing on</primary></indexterm>

<para>The FreeBSD project has a whole <ulink
url="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/ports.html">chapter</ulink>
in their Handbook describing the package and port installation
processes.  A brief summary of the process follows.</para>

<sect3><title>Installation of the binary package</title>

<para>The easiest way to install the binary Nmap package is to run
<command>pkg_add -r nmap</command>.  You can then run the same command
with the <option>zenmap</option> argument if you want the X-Window
front-end.  If you wish to obtain the package manually instead,
retrieve it from <ulink
url="http://freshports.org/security/nmap" /> and <ulink url="http://freshports.org/security/zenmap"/> or
the CDROM and run <command>pkg_add <replaceable>packagename.tgz</replaceable></command>.
</para>
</sect3>


<sect3><title>Installation using the source ports tree</title>
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>The ports tree is often installed with the system
itself (usually in <filename>/usr/ports</filename>).  If you do not already have it,
specific installation instructions are provided in the FreeBSD Handbook
chapter referenced above.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>As root, execute the following command (replace <filename>/usr/ports</filename> with your local ports directory if it differs):</para>
<para><command>cd /usr/ports/security/nmap &amp;&amp; make install clean</command></para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-netbsd"><title>NetBSD Binary Package Instructions</title>
<indexterm><primary>NetBSD, installing on</primary></indexterm>
<para>NetBSD has packaged Nmap for an enormous number of platforms, from the normal i386 to PlayStation 2, PowerPC, VAX, SPARC, MIPS, Amiga, ARM, and several platforms that I have never even heard of!  A list of NetBSD Nmap packages is available from <ulink url="ftp://ftp.netbsd.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/pkgsrc/net/nmap/README.html" /> and a description of using their package system to install applications is available at <ulink url="http://netbsd.org/Documentation/pkgsrc/using.html" />.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="inst-other-platforms"><title>Amiga, HP-UX, IRIX, and Other Platforms</title>
<indexterm><primary>AmigaOS, installing on</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>HP-UX, installing on</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>IRIX, installing on</primary></indexterm>



<para>One of the wonders of open source development is that resources
are often directed towards what people find exciting rather than having
an exclusive focus on profits as most corporations do.  It is along
those lines that the Amiga port came about.
Diego Casorran<indexterm><primary>Casorran, Diego</primary></indexterm> performed
most of the work and sent in a clean patch which was integrated into
the main Nmap distribution.  In general, AmigaOS users should be able
to simply follow the source compilation instructions in <xref
linkend="inst-source" />.  You may encounter a few hurdles on some
systems, but I presume that must be part of the fun for Amiga
fanatics.</para>

<para>Nmap supports many proprietary Unix flavors such as HP-UX and
SGI IRIX.  The Nmap project depends on the user community to
help maintain adequate support for these systems.  If you have trouble, try
sending a report with full details to the <citetitle>nmap-dev</citetitle> mailing list<indexterm><primary><citetitle>nmap-dev</citetitle> mailing list</primary></indexterm>, as described in <xref linkend="man-bugs"/>.  Also let us know if
you develop a patch which
improves support on your platform so we can incorporate it into Nmap.</para>  
</sect1>

<sect1 id="inst-removing-nmap"><title>Removing Nmap</title>
<indexterm><primary>uninstallation</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>removal</primary></indexterm>

<para>If your purpose for removing Nmap is
simply to upgrade to the latest version, you can usually use the
upgrade option provided by most binary package managers.  Similarly,
installing the latest source code (as described in <xref
linkend="inst-source" />) generally overwrites any
previous from-source installations.  Removing Nmap is a good idea if
you are changing install methods (such as from source to RPM or vice
versa) or if you are not using Nmap anymore and you care about the few
megabytes of disk space it consumes.</para>

<para>How to remove Nmap depends on how
you installed it initially (see previous sections).  Ease of removal (and other maintenance) is a major advantage of most binary packages.  For example, when Nmap is installed using
the RPM<indexterm><primary>RPM</primary></indexterm>
system common on Linux distributions, it can be removed by
running the command <command>rpm -e nmap
zenmap</command> as root.  Analogous options are offered by
most other package managers&mdash;consult their documentation for further
information.</para>

<para>If you installed Nmap from the Windows installer, simply open the <application>Control Panel</application>, select <quote>Add or Remove Programs</quote> and select the <quote>Remove</quote> button for Nmap.  You can also remove WinPcap unless you need it for other applications such as Wireshark.</para>

<para>If you installed Nmap from source
code, removal is slightly more difficult.  If you still have the build
directory available (where you initially ran <command>make
install</command>), you can remove Nmap by
running <command>make uninstall</command>.  If you no longer have that
build directory, type <command>nmap -V</command> to
obtain the Nmap version number.  Then
download that source tarball for that version of
Nmap from <ulink url="http://nmap.org/dist/" /> or <ulink url="http://nmap.org/dist-old/" />.
Uncompress the tarball and change into the newly created directory
(<filename>nmap-<replaceable>version</replaceable></filename>).  Run
<command>./configure</command>, including any install-path options that you specified
the first time (such as <option>--prefix</option> or
<option>--datadir</option>).  Then run <command>make
uninstall</command>.  Alternatively, you can simply delete all the
Nmap-related files.  If you used a default source install of Nmap
versions 4.50 or higher, the following commands remove it.</para>
<screen>
# <userinput>cd /usr/local</userinput>
# <userinput>rm -f bin/nmap bin/nmapfe bin/xnmap</userinput>
# <userinput>rm -f man/man1/nmap.1 man/man1/zenmap.1</userinput>
# <userinput>rm -rf share/nmap</userinput>
# <userinput>./bin/uninstall_zenmap</userinput>
</screen>
<para>You may have to adjust the above commands slightly if you
specified <option>--prefix</option> or other install-path option when
first installing Nmap.  The files relating to zenmap, nmapfe, and xnmap do not exist if you did not install the <application>Zenmap</application> frontend.</para>

</sect1>

<indexterm class="endofrange" startref="install-indexterm"/>
</chapter>
